Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is צדי דלד. tzaddi
daled. We pick up at the very bottom of צדי גימל עמוד
בית. tzaddi gimmel amud bet. We had just read the משנה mishnah
where the משנה mishnah talked about when you sell various things: if
you sell grain, how much, or if you sell figs or wine,
what percentage is considered to be tolerable or acceptable that they are...
with the wine that it would be spoiled, with the figs that
maybe it would have worms in it, with the grain that
it would have טינופת, tinofet, some type of dross or some type
of extraneous material mixed up in it? And we're going to discuss
in the גמרא gemara what that extraneous material is. So what is
sort of considered a tolerable limit where the buyer understands that that
sometimes happens and it's not the basis of a מקח טעות, mekach
taos, whereas more than that obviously is not acceptable and then he
has to be, presumably he would have to be reimbursed.
Question as we mentioned is let's say you have 11 out of
the 10 percent of wine that was going bad of the barrels;
if you had 11 barrels out of 100, do you get reimbursed
for all 11 or just for the one that's over the limit?
So anyway, those types of issues we'll see somewhat of today, or
a lot of that today.
By the way, what you do not want to do in this
regard, or maybe you do, is go ahead and find out how
much from the US government, the FDA perspective, is acceptable animal parts
per million in your food, because there definitely is a tolerable limit
of little animal parts, little bug parts in your food or whatever,
which you would be shocked what that amount is. So anyway, let's
take a look at the גמרא. gemara. That's actually for an איסור
אכילה. issur achila. This is actually for מקח וממכר. mekach umimkar. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. We'll start again from
the beginning of the גמרא, gemara, two lines from the bottom on
צדי גימל עמוד בית. tzaddi gimmel amud bet. תני רב קטינא. tani
Raf Katina. רב קטינא Raf Katina taught, it's interesting, רב קטינא Raf
Katina is going to teach something about
קטניות. kitnios. רובע קטניות לסאה. rova kitnios l'seah. So when the משנה
mishnah says a רובע, rova, a quarter of a קב, kav, which
is 1/24th, which is 4 percent, is acceptable of some type of
extraneous material mixed in. It says טינופת, tinofet, literally filth, dirt. So
he says what that really means is that means that if you
have some legumes mixed in, because wild legumes will grow together with
the grain and a certain amount will mix in. So the גמרא
gemara says ועפרית לא? v'afuriss lo? So does that mean to suggest
that dirt, there's no tolerable amount? You should totally wash the grain
or whatever. Meaning what the משנה's mishnah referring to is sort of
a tolerable mix of this legumes, but the dirt is not tolerable
to have this amount? והאמר רבה בר בר חנה כתוספא כתוסבא v'ha'amar
Rava bar Bar Chana katuspa katusba משמיה דרבא, mishmei d'Rava, doesn't רבה
בר בר חנה Rava bar Bar Chana say כתוספא katuspa כתוסבא katusba
משמיה דרבא: mishmei d'Rava: בורר צרור מגרנו של חבירו? borer tzror mi'gorono
shel chaveiro?
If you go ahead and you go to your friend's threshing floor
and there he has this mound of
grain which he's got planning on putting in the sacks and selling,
and you figure you'll go ahead and you'll do him a favor,
so you start cleaning it and throwing out some rocks and some
dirt. So
the הלכה halacha is נותן לו דמי חטין. nosein lo dmei chitin.
So you have to pay him the volume of the dirt, you
have to pay him in חטין. chitin. Why? Because if you had
not done this favor for him, he would have bagged all that
grain straight into these five-pound bags, and that would have had a
certain amount of dirt, and that would have been acceptable. And now
because you took the dirt out, he has to put in the
five-pound bag, instead of a little bit of dirt to make it
weigh the full five pounds, it's going to have to replace it
with grain. So something that could have been sold to the buyer
and would have with a certain mixture of dirt, you've removed the
dirt and forced him effectively to replace that with grain. So your
removal of the dirt cost him grain. So therefore you have to
pay him for the weight of that dirt in grain. נותן לו
דמי חטין. nosein lo dmei chitin. There's an interesting debate of the
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafos whether this is גרמא בנזיקין grama b'nezikin
or whether this is considered no real מזיק. mazik. The רשב"ם Rashbam
says it's גרמא. grama. You didn't actually damage anything, the wheat is
still the way it was, you just indirectly now because of the
rules of מקח וממכר mekach umimkar forced him to fill up his
bag with a little bit more extra grain. So that's a type
of גרמא, grama, גרמי, garmi, it would be according to the approach
that certain types of גרמא grama of indirect causation you have to
pay for. תוספות Tosafos says no, it's real מזיק. mazik. You had
a pile of grain
that was worth whatever it was worth, this guy did this act,
he removed some dirt. So if he removed an ounce of dirt
and now this pile will sell
as four pounds 15 ounces, 16... 16... four...
this pile will now sell as four pounds and 15 ounces and
it won't sell as five pounds. You damaged that pile of grain.
That pile of grain is now worth less, can't be sold for
as much money. So there's an interesting question whether you conceptualize. It
does as an entire pile of grain that is now worth less
money, or would you say you just, you know, you just sifted
some stuff out, you just caused him indirectly some some type of
a loss. But either way, what's clear is is that he is
allowed to sell grain with a certain amount of dirt in it,
okay? And as so, how can you say that the משנה Mishna
is only referring to a tolerable amount of קטניות? legumes? This statement
makes it clear that there's a tolerable amount of dirt as well.
So then there's the beginning.
Is it dirt in the sense of אדמה Adama or is it
לכלוך? Lichluch?
Well,
I think it's all. Like here's a צרור Tzror which is like
a rock, so that's not like dirt. But it's אפרורית Afruris like
any type of, I think, dust, I think it's all those things.
Anything that would come, you know, any time when you talk about
like washing off fruit, so it's the type of stuff you would
wash it off from, you know, the dirt, the rocks, the dust,
all those things. I don't think we're distinguishing, but it means as
opposed to some different type of a food product, as opposed to
like the קטנית, Kitnis, okay?
That's טינופת. Tinofes. That's טינופת. Tinofes. That's right, that's more consistent with
the word in the משנה Mishna of טינופת. Tinofes. Exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying the fact that you're trying to say טינופת
Tinofes means, you know, legumes and it sounds like dirt is, you
know, dust, טינופת, Tinofes, other types of things are not tolerable, but
here it's clear that that is considered something that's sold with the
grain. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, we didn't mean to exclude
that completely. The גמרא Gemara says קטנית רובע. Kitnis Rova. When it
comes to like legumes, up to a רובע, Rova, again, a רובע
Rova of a קב kav for a סאה, se'ah, like one, it's
like 4%. Up to a רובע Rova is tolerable. אפרורית, Afruris, if
it's however types of like dust and dirt or whatever, פחות מרובע.
pachos mi'rova. So we're not saying it's not tolerable. We're just saying
it's a different limit, less than a רובע, Rova, of course which
begs the question how much less. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says well,
a tiny bit less. So then there's really not much of a
difference. You know, this is acceptable 4%, this is acceptable under 4%.
You know, so what, so it's not a huge difference. Anyway, but
the point is is that he's saying the משנה Mishna that says
a רובע Rova is the קטנית, Kitnis, is the legumes. Other things,
dirt and dust and rocks or whatever, the tolerable limit is a
little bit less. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay, ואפרורית רובע לא, Va'Afruris Rova Lo, are you telling me
a full רובע, Rova, a full 4% is not acceptable for like
the dirt and the dust? הא והתניא, Ha v'hatanya, but we taught
in a ברייתא, Braisa, המוכר פירות לחבירו חיטין, Ha'Mochar Peros L'Chaveiro Chitin,
מקבל עליו רובע קטנית לסאה. mekabel alav rova kitnis l'se'ah. So here
actually you see what was driving רב קטינא's Rav Katina claim, because
a ברייתא Braisa explicitly identifies that the type of thing that could
be mixed with the grain that would be normal to expect would
be these legumes. If you sell fruit to your friend, it now
tells you what type of fruit. If it's grain, so then he
accepts, you know, what's tolerable is a רובע Rova for a, you
know, סאה. se'ah. A רובע קטנית לסאה. Rova Kitnis l'Se'ah. A רובע
Rova of legumes for a סאה, se'ah, again about 4%. שעורים, Se'orim,
if it's barley, so מקבל עליו רובע נשובת לסאה. mekabel alav rova
nishoves l'se'ah. Same amount, 4%, but as opposed to the קטנית, Kitnis,
the legumes, it's נשובת. Nishoves. נשובת Nishoves the רשב"ם Rashbam says it
means like straw that gets blown by the wind and gets mixed
up. That would be more normal by barley. עדשים, Adashim, if it's
lentils, מקבל עליו רובע אפרורית לסאה. mekabel alav rova afruris l'se'ah. So
there it's dirt, okay? And up so there the גמרא Gemara is
assuming, although you could assume the opposite, but the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that if dirt gets mixed up with the lentils, dirt gets
mixed up with everything. So if that's a tolerable amount of dirt
for the lentils, presumably it would be a tolerable amount of dirt
for everything and it wouldn't be limited to lentils. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי לאו הוא הדין לחיטין ולשעורין, mai lav hu hadin
l'chitin u'l'se'orin, that if that dirt is if is tolerable for lentils,
presumably it's tolerable for other other things,
wheat and barley? It says no, שאני עדשים דמאקר אקרי להו. shani
adashim de'ma'aker akri lehu. No, no, no. Lentils, you pull straight out
of the ground. You don't harvest with a scythe, you know, and
it doesn't grow like high above the ground like wheat and barley,
right? That doesn't really, you know, the grains of the wheat and
barley aren't touching the dirt. So that dirt is not a normal
thing to get mixed up. The stuff that's growing there close to
the ground and that you're pulling out from the ground, so some
dirt gets mixed in with the, you know, in the processing. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אבל חיטי ושעורי לא, aval chitin v'se'ori lo,
so the גמרא Gemara says okay, so that's why dirt is that's
only by lentils. By wheat and barley, this actually now is a
support for רב קטינא. Rav Katina. It seems like dirt is not
tolerable at all, or certainly not to the same degree. Seems like
a nice support for רב קטינא. Rav Katina. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara says אלא טעמא דעדשים, ela ta'amei
d'adashim, fine, you're telling me the reason that dirt is tolerable is
we're talking about lentils דמאקר אקרי להו, de'ma'aker akri lehu, those are
torn, those are like uprooted directly from the ground. אבל חיטי ושעורי
לא, aval chitin v'se'ori lo, but it sounds like wheat and barley
dirt is not tolerable, certainly not to the same amount.
תפשוט מינה Tifshot minah דחיטי ושעורי דאפרורית לא מקבל, de'chitin v'se'ori de'afruris
lo mekabel, so so we should use this as a support for
רב קטינא, Rav Katina, and the right which is true, the simple
sense of this ברייתא Braisa sounds like when it comes to wheat
and barley... A dirt is not considered acceptable, certainly not the same
amount of dirt is acceptable. So this is a nice support for
רב קטינא. Rav Katina. So the גמרא Gemara says,
תפשוט מינה דחיטי ושערי דאפרוותא לא מקבלי. Tifshot mineh de-chitti u-se'arei de-afravta
lo mekablei. The גמרא Gemara says
no, לעולם חיטי ושערי
מקבלי. Le-olam chitti u-se'arei mekabel. No, really you could say that even
by wheat and barley, a certain dirt is tolerable and maybe even
the same amount, maybe even a רובע. rova. So if it's the
same amount, why do we only mention it by lentils since lentils
obviously will have more dirt? The גמרא Gemara says עדשים איצטריכא ליה,
Adashim itzterich lei, you had to mention it by lentils. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I might have thought כיון דמיעקר עקרי, kivan
de-mi'akar akri, since lentils you pull up straight from the ground, יותר
מרובע נמי מקבל, yoteir mi-rova nami mekabel,
maybe with them even more than four percent of dirt is acceptable,
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that it's not. Okay, so basically
what we have is a ברייתא Braita that speaks about tolerable dirt
by lentils and tolerable legumes by wheat. So that certainly seems the
basis of רב קטינא Rav Katina that by wheat what's tolerable is
lentils, not dirt. And if there is a certain amount of tolerable
dirt by wheat it's going to be a much lesser amount or
somewhat dirt, which is certainly the simple sense of the ברייתא Braita
that we've just now presented. But the גמרא Gemara says maybe not,
maybe the same amount of dirt that's tolerable by lentils is tolerable
by wheat and the חידוש chiddush is that even by lentils you're
limited to this amount of dirt and no more. Fine. Okay, but
anyway that's the type of things that are normally mixed up and
what are the tolerable limits. Now we have a get to this
question related to the question I asked about wine, the גמרא Gemara
goes to ask it about the about the wheat. Question I asked
about wine is if eleven barrels as opposed to ten out of
the hundred are bad, do you have to reimburse me for all
eleven or just for the extra one that went over the limit?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to ask that question about
the wheat. What if more than this amount had you know had
legumes or had dirt or whatever it was that's mixed up, more
than the tolerable amount? How much do you now have to reimburse
me for you the seller? So let's take a look. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא, Rav Huna,
אם בא לנפות, im ba lenapot,
if you want to come to sift out the wheat, מנפה את
כולו, menafeh et kulo, you sift it all out. And of course
they're not just telling me that here I am on the buyer,
if I want to sift out my wheat I should be welcome
to sift out my wheat, like okay, of course, whatever I want
with my wheat. It means if I am saying to you the
seller like I am going to sift this out because I think
there's too much and then I sift it out and I find
that there's actually like you know more than four percent, it's five
percent, then I've removed the full five percent and by saying that
I sifted it all out, it means and now you have to
reimburse me for the full five percent of the stuff that I
removed. Four percent was acceptable, it turned out it was five percent,
I am entitled to remove all of the bad stuff and ask
you now to reimburse me. So the basic point is is that
when you go over the limit of what's tolerable, you have to
reimburse the buyer for the full amount. Okay, but it's important that
we're going to see in a minute that in the case of
the wheat and the grain etcetera and the barley that that can
only sort of be determined or cleaned out by the process of
sifting. So let's take a look why that's relevant. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אמרי לה דינא ואמרי לה קנסא. Amreilei dina
ve-amreilei knasa. Some said the reason of רב הונא Rav Huna is
an actual דין, din, you know, that you're legally entitled now to
be fully reimbursed. Others say it's a fine for the seller. So
what's the two ways of thinking about it? אמרי לה דינא, Amreilei
dina, one way to say it is that it's actually legally entitled.
מאן דיהיב זוזי אפירי שפיר יהיב, Man de-yeihiv zuzei apeiri shapir yeihiv,
when you go ahead and you pay your money for the wheat,
you are expecting you really are entitled to get a full five
pounds of wheat, you're not buying 4.9
pounds of wheat and 0.1 pounds of legumes or whatever it is,
you're really entitled to get the full five pounds of wheat. Okay,
ורובע לא טרח אינשי, ve-rova lo tarach inishi,
but up to a certain amount it's not worth for my effort
to like to sift it out, okay? And it's not worth I
guess you know your effort as a seller to sift it out,
but basically here it is you're selling me the wheat, so technically
speaking the idea is is that I really should get a full
weight for my you know for what I'm paying for. But because
it is so much effort either for you or for me to
sift it out and it's not worth for either of us you
know that amount of effort, I'm like מוחל mochel that amount. Okay,
fine, whatever, I know that there's a certain amount and in theory
if I were to sift it out or whatever you'd have to
reimburse me but it's just not worth my effort to go through
that process, not worth your effort to go through that process. Okay,
so יותר מרובע טרח אינשי, yoteir mi-rova tarach inishi,
but once it's more than a רובע, rova, then the amount of
effort it takes to sift it out compared to how much is
the actual amount of grain that I'm losing out on, it's actually
worth the effort for me to like get rid of the dirt
and to ask for replacement, you know and to get it to
be replaced. דכיון דטרח טרח בכולו. dekivan de-tarach tarach bekulo. And once
it's worth the effort effort, it's like it's worth the effort for
like I'm also already gonna bother to sift it out, I'm gonna
sift it all out. So what does that mean? So it sounds
like the best way, you know, I think to explain this is
I think תוספות Tosafot or let me see if I can find
a good line here the רשבם. Rashbam. But the basic point is
like this is that because I had a hard time really getting
my head around what exactly the גמרא Gemara means, so I think
תוספות Tosafot has a good line, let me just see if I
can find it to explain this.
He says like this.
Hold on a second.
Yeah, so I think it's a later רשבם. Rashbam. I don't remember
exactly where it is. But the basic point is is that, you
know, is that like I'm מוכל mochel up to a point that's
not worth any of our efforts to bother to remove. Once it's
a certain amount that there's so much here that's mixed up that
it really is not tolerable to, you know, it goes beyond sort
of the מחילה mechila limit. Okay, because now it is worth the
effort to remove it. So this amount I'm not מוכל, mochel, and
since I'm not מוכל, mochel, it's not just I care about the
extra one percent, it's like I look at the entire amount, right?
The entire amount, it's not worth it for me to leave it
this way. Once it hits this amount, I would want to put
in the effort to remove all the dirt. So since I would
want to put in that effort once it hits that amount, I'm
not מוכל mochel on any of this. Oh yeah.
Right, it's like once you get started, once you have to put
in the effort, then like...
Right, exactly, in for a penny, in for a pound. Yeah, exactly,
exactly. So yeah, I'm just I guess what I'm struggling with is
I'm trying to figure out like whose effort are we talking about.
Like, I mean I think we're talking about my, if it's you're
the seller's effort, so what do I care about your effort? I
could say if I expect the full five pounds, then, you know,
but somehow it's like if, I think the way the רשבם Rashbam
says it is, is that but okay how much dirt is there
there? There's no way to determine how much dirt is there until,
you know, I would actually, I the buyer would sift it out
and then prove it to you and show you look there's this
amount of dirt, reimburse me. And the assumption is that for smaller
than a certain amount, I'm just gonna say forget it, that's not
worth my time to go try to determine the amount of dirt
and whatever, so there's a presumed מחילה. mechila. But once it is
worth my time because the total amount that I'm sacrificing is too
big, then it is then, then I'm not מוכל mochel any part
of it. So then I want full reimbursement. Okay, so that's the
position of
דינא. Dina. Okay, ואמרי לה טעמא. V'amri lei ta'ama. Some say it's
the following: רובע שכיח. Rova shchiach. Really we assume that the guy
is מוכל mochel however amount of dirt there is which just happens
naturally, like, you know, I don't expect the farmer to go ahead
and to wash it and the whole thing. So however much dirt
I'm מוכל. mochel. So why more than a certain amount does he
have to reimburse me?
So it says though רובע שכיח Rova shchiach because רובע rova of
dirt or whatever legumes is common. יותר לא שכיח. Yoter lo shchiach.
More, which turned out to be this case, is not common. דאיהו
דעריב. De'ihu de'ariv. So our explanation of why is there so much
mixed in is, it must be the farmer did it intentionally. The
way you could also look at this is not necessarily that we
like suspect everybody, you know, naturally assume that, but it also could
be seen as preventative. If we don't have a serious consequence for
a high degree of contamination, right, so then then what's gonna stop
people from just trying to more highly contaminate it? So there has
to be a pretty serious consequence, right? And so if you think
about it, oh, up to ten percent up to four percent I
can get away with. More than four percent if all I had
to do was reimburse you for the amount over more than four
percent, it's like the problem of the תורה, Torah, what's to stop
a guy being a גזלן? gazlan? You know what the consequence of
being a גזלן gazlan is? Give it back. So if the consequence
of me having more than four percent in it was to reimburse
you for the more than four percent, then there's no loss, there's
no incentive for me to care to even let me be sloppy,
not to do the job of washing and cleaning and checking that
I should, or even to intentionally. But if the consequence is that
if it's more than the tolerable amount I have to reimburse you
for everything, right, then that's gonna get me to be careful. Okay,
so יותר מרובע, Yoter merova, רובע שכיח, Rova shchiach, יותר לא שכיח,
Yoter lo shchiach, דאיהו דעריב, De'ihu de'ariv,
and we're gonna assume that you did it intentionally or I'm throwing
in maybe through negligence, one way or the other, therefore it's gonna
be a consequence that's gonna hurt you once you go over that
limit. וכיון דעריב קנסוהו רבנן וכולי V'keivan de'ariv kansu'u rabbanan v'chulei and
since you did that we're gonna, once you did that we're gonna
fine you for the entire amount, not just for the overage amount.
Okay, so that's two different explanations. One explanation is once you hit
that amount there's up till that amount you're מוכל, mochel, more than
an amount you're not מוכל mochel on any once it hit once
it's past the threshold you're not מוכל mochel on any of it.
And the other approach is no, maybe you are מוכל mochel on
the first four percent... percent, but we're fining the guy and making
him reimburse to prevent this from happening.
Okay, מתיב. maysiv. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask a
series of questions and it's where and it's not always clear whether
we're asking against the approach that it's a fine or against the
approach that it's a דין. din. But let's take a look at
the questions. Okay, כור סאה שיש בה רובע ממין אחר ימעיט. Kor
se'ah she'yesh bah rova m'min acher yema'it.
So here again is a הלכה halacha of a רובע, rova, but
this is now not talking about מקח וממכר, mekach umemkar, it's talking
about כלאים. kilayim. I'm going ahead and I'm planting wheat, and mixed
up in my wheat seed, because look, that's the flip side, I
bought this bag of wheat seed from you and it has these
legumes in it. So I take this wheat seed and I'm not
eating it, not wheat seed, whatever, wheat grain, and I'm not eating
it and I'm planting it. So am I now עובר over on
the transgression of planting כלאים? kilayim? Okay, so it's the same question,
if it's got a mixture in it and I'm planting it, maybe
I'm planting כלאים. kilayim. So the הלכה halacha is, is that if
there is a רובע, rova, now remember a רובע rova was exactly
the amount of the tolerable limit, so if there's a רובע rova
of this other type of a grain or whatever seed mixed into
it, ימעיט, yema'it, I have to decrease that amount of that other
grain. Now, but it doesn't say I have to completely remove it.
So I've got my wheat grain mixed in with it is some
legume seeds and exactly a רובע, rova, and I just have to
get it just under a רובע rova to avoid the prohibition of
כלאים. kilayim. By the way, that's fascinating, why am I avoiding the
prohibition of כלאים? kilayim? I'm actually have other seeds mixed in here,
right? Is there a tolerable amount for כלאים kilayim as well? So
let's take a look, but it says I have to lower it
and it doesn't say I have to completely remove it. All right,
סברוה, savruhah, we
assume דרובע דכלאים כיתר מרובע דהכא דמי, de'rova de'kilayim k'yoser mi'rova de'hacha
dami, that a רובע rova of כלאים kilayim is like more than
a רובע, rova, meaning it's you've passed the acceptable line. So for
whatever reason, by מקח וממכר, mekach umemkar, by selling, more than a
רובע rova is not tolerable. By כלאים kilayim a רובע rova is
not tolerable. But once you hit the non-acceptable limit, we assume the
הלכה halacha will be the same. דקתני ימעיט, de'katani yema'it, and all
we have to say is, is that you go to, you get
it just within the acceptable limit, you don't have to totally remove
it. Now, what is the basis of comparison? How do the laws
of כלאים kilayim have anything to do with the question of my
liability to you in terms of מקח וממכר? mekach umemkar? So תוספות
Tosafot says we're talking according to the approach that it's a קנס.
knas. And here's the idea also what תוספות Tosafot says is, we're
not talking about לכתחילה lechatchilah as I can plant a seed, okay,
maybe לכתחילה lechatchilah I can't plant any amount mixed in. What we're
talking about is, I've already planted it and now I see that
unbeknownst to me, I planted some legume seeds as well and I've
got the כלאים kilayim growing together. Now תוספות Tosafot also points out
by the way,
that when you're talking about כלאי זרעים, kilay zera'im, not כלאי כרם,
kilay kerem, when you don't
have grape seed involved and vines involved, what grows is not forbidden
to be eaten and not forbidden בהנאה, be'hana'ah, okay, like that's for
example why you can eat these various types of hybrid fruit, you
know, there's no איסור issur of אכילה achilah and הנאה hana'ah by
כלאים kilayim when it's not כלאי הכרם. kilay hakerem. So but what
I'm not allowed to do is I'm not allowed to plant it.
And by extension, if it's continuing to grow and I'm not doing
anything about it, that's a concept called מקיים, mekayeim, like I am
willfully keeping it and that's sort of like, you know, not directly
planting it, but sort of like planting it, keeping it growing and
so on. So here it is, I planted this stuff, it's taken
root, this is the way תוספות Tosafot explains it, and now you're
going to force me to pull up some, okay? So and so
now, so תוספות Tosafot understands that this obligation we're assuming, this obligation
to uproot what is growing of the קטנית kitnis is a type
of a קנס. knas. Okay, you planted too much, you allowed too
much of this other of this other seed to be mixed in,
okay, we're going to fine you and force you to uproot it.
And nevertheless, or maybe we should force you, you did something not
acceptable. Why is it enough to just get it to the acceptable
limit? Why don't we make a קנס knas and say once you're
beginning to uproot it, you should uproot everything? So that's the analogy.
It seems to be evidence that we don't go ahead and make
a קנס. knas. Now you could still say there's different motivations to
make a קנס, knas, one is the person doing some possible unintentional
עבירה aveirah of כלאים, kilayim,
another is people trying to cheat in business, you know, maybe there's
a lot more incentive to cheat in business than who knows what,
you know, maybe we make a קנס knas in one place not
in the other case. But nevertheless, at least on the surface of
it, that's the comparison. In both cases you pass the tolerable limit,
why here is it enough just to get within the tolerable limit
and we don't fine you and say you have to uproot it
all? And in our case, according to at least the one version
is there is a קנס knas and you have to give pay
back the full amount. So that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, so מאי, mai, so דקתני ימעיט, de'katani yema'it, it's
enough to get within the acceptable limit and we don't make a
fine. It says לא, lo, no, it's not a good comparison.
רובע דכלאים כרובע דהכא דמי. rova de'kilayim k'rova de'hacha dami. No, they're
actually the same, which makes Sense, right? If it's considered a tolerable
limit in terms of a mixture of מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, then
presumably and it's very, right, it's the same רובע, rova, presumably it's
the same tolerable limit for laws of כלאים. kilayim. Like that's not,
that's a natural amount that gets mixed up, that's not really considered
something extraneous. Okay, and therefore if I plant כלאים kilayim up to
and including a רובע, rova, that actually is not a violation. All
right, and since it's not a vio- again, that actually makes sense.
If it's an acceptable amount to be mixed in when I sell,
and that's sort of seen as the normal thing, it's not a
violation of כלאים. kilayim. Okay, so that's why fundamentally here you're not
yet in violation, you're right at the line. You have a רובע
rova and that actually technically is acceptable by כלאים kilayim the same
way it's acceptable by מקח וממכר. mekach umimkar. אי הכי i hachi
says the גמרא, Gemara, מאי ימעיט? mai yamiet? So then why do
you have to do anything if it's within the acceptable limit? משום
חומרא דכלאים. mishum chumra dekilayim. Okay, you're really not obligated, but because
you're right on the line, we want you to decrease it because,
you know, you're going to be over on this prohibition. So that
allows the גמרא, Gemara, because of this difference, right, in our case
it says more than a רובע's rova a problem. By כלאים kilayim
it says if it is a רובע rova you have to be
ימעיט, yamiet, it allows גמרא Gemara to say you're not yet violated
by כלאים. kilayim. You're about to violate, but you haven't, you're just
at the line. And because you have not yet violated, right, that's
why it's saying that what do you call it, that we allow
you to just reduce it a little bit and you don't have
to remove it completely. When you're really in violation, we would fine
you and you'd have to either completely remove it by כלאים kilayim
or completely reimburse the person when you're in violation. But since you're
not yet in violation, we're allowing you to just decrease it without
completely removing it, yes.
But does this mean you're purposely doing כלאים? kilayim?
So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to continue, so excellent. So
גמרא Gemara says like this: So אי הכי i hachi says the
גמרא, Gemara, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of
that. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose אומר omer יבור, yivor, you should like
בורר, borer, you should select out, meaning completely remove it. So what's
their debate? If they were talking- if it was that they were
you were in violation, then this debate would be exactly this question:
when you're in violation, do you have to completely remove it or
just get it lower than the line? Okay, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
would say you get it lower than the line and רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose says you completely remove it. But now you're saying that
you're not in violation. So if you're not in violation, why would
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose be so strict to demand you completely remove
the extraneous material? So the גמרא Gemara says: אי אמרת בשלמא דיותר
מרובע כנפש דמי, i amart bishlama d'yoter merova k'nefesh dami, if this
was considered to be like by a מקח וממכר mekach umimkar case
when you went over the line and here too it was over
the line and you were in violation,
והא קמיפלגי, v'ha kamiflagi, that would have been the debate. תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma סבר savar לא קנסינן היתרא אטו איסורא. lo kansinan hatara
atu issura. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would be of the position
that since- that even though we're going to fine you or, you
know, force you to reduce it, we're not going to force you
to reduce the stuff that is tolerable, we're only going to force
you to reduce the intolerable amount but not the entire amount, not
the part that's היתר heter that was acceptable. ורבי יוסי v'Rabbi Yose
סבר savar קנסינן. kansinan. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
no, once you violate, so if you violated מקח וממכר mekach umimkar
you reimburse the full amount if you went over the line, and
if you violated by כלאים kilayim you reduce the entire amount, קנסינן,
kansinan, and we're going to fine you and force you to reduce
the whole thing, to remove the whole thing. אלא אי אמרת כרובע
דמי, ella i amart kerova dami, but if it's like- if it's
not like over the line, it's like the standard רובע rova of
מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, it's within the tolerable limit and we're just
being strict here, so מאי יבור, mai yivor, why does רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose say you have to remove the entire amount? You aren't
even in violation yet. So the גמרא Gemara says, like Jenna said:
התם היינו טעמא דרבי יוסי משום דמחזי כמקיים כלאים. hasam hainu ta'ama
deRabbi Yose mishum d'mechzi k'mekayem kilayim.
Because if you actually begin a process of removing and then you
stop, I removed five- you know, I moved this amount and the
rest fine, just leave it there. You're like actively leaving it. You're
actively saying I'm okay with the fact that the rest of the
stuff is continuing to grow. If you're just ignoring it, you're not
okay, you're not not okay, you're just ignoring the problem. Okay, but
if you're actively removing some and leaving the rest, that's like you
are willing- willingly- you're saying I- you know, that you're willingly saying
that I want the rest to continue to grow. So the way
the גמרא's Gemara dealt with it is, it seems on the face
of it this could have been a perfect way of saying like
this question is debate between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yose, once you violate do you just have to get
below the line or do you have to correct the whole problem?
Right, or is the גמרא Gemara actually saying that no, that we're
talking about a special case you haven't yet violated and רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose the reason he's being so strict is just because of
a special כלאים kilayim problem, then it looks like you're actively being
מקיים mekayem the כלאים. kilayim. Yeah, yes. Go ahead.
No, but like, so this is a weeding kind of thing, you're
now pulling
yourself back from כלאים.
kilayim. Exactly. So is it practical to pull everything out? Like I
mean, is the debate
between...
I mean, what do you mean practical, like the amount of effort?
I mean, you just go everywhere and every time you see a
kidneys plant, you pull it out. I don't know, I mean it's
a lot of work I assume. Right, right.
Okay, I think the voices are between... I see. Okay, if you
can't get everything out,
so you're saying the whole field? Right, I see. So you're saying...
right,
it's an endless job, it's an endless job, right. So you're sort
of saying that like according to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, right, what
you're sort of saying is like according to רב יוסף Rav Yosef
that it's, I mean, according to the response to רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, is you're not being מקיים. mekayem. It's like, it's an impossible
task to get everything out. So the fact that I'm not finishing
the task is not saying that I'm willingly and I'm happy about
it. Right, right.
No, the way the ראש, Rosh, the way תוספות Tosafot explains it
is that you've already planted the seed and this is the percentage
that's growing. If you're looking at the English, they're probably following the
רשבם. Rashbam. The רשבם Rashbam said that we're talking about that you
actually have seeds in your hand and it's a mixture and you're
choosing whether to plant them or not. I was choosing to read
it תוספות's Tosafot way because I just think it's, it reads better.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah, the English is reading it. תוספות Tosafot says we're talking
about what's actually growing and uprooting. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. Okay. תא שמע. Ta shema.
Now
this, so that at least was within the world of seeds and
actually was קטניות kitniyot mixed up with חטין, chittin, it was roughly
the same amount, it was רובע, rova, יתר מרובע. yeter mi-rova. Now
we're going to bring something that's completely unrelated, but once you're talking
about קנס, kenas, the גמרא Gemara feels free to quote these more
far-reaching examples. תא שמע. Ta shema. This might, people might remember this
from the first פרק perek of בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. שנים שהפקידו
אצל אחד, Shenayim she-hifkidu etzel echad, זה מנה וזה מאתים. zeh maneh
ve-zeh matayim.
So two people, so, so Jen and I both gave Gloria here
some money to watch for us. One of us gave Gloria a
hundred dollars, and one of us gave Gloria two hundred dollars. Okay,
and guess what happened? Nobody took any notes, nobody had any documentation,
and זה אומר מאתים שלי, zeh omer matayim sheli,
and I come and I say Jen, the two hundred was mine,
וזה אומר מאתים שלי, ve-zeh omer matayim sheli, and Jen says no,
the two hundred was mine. And Gloria can't remember. So what's she
supposed to do? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, נותן לזה
מנה ולזה מנה והשאר יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, noten la-zeh maneh
ve-la-zeh maneh ve-ha-she-ar ye-hei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu, each one gets back
a hundred because we each definitely gave you a hundred, and the
third hundred is held in escrow until אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Ha-Navi comes
or until somehow, some evidence comes to light or one of us
confesses up. Okay, so now there's a question about one of us
is lying and nobody is being fined. You're only fining the person,
or actually you're not even fining the liar, you're actually fining the
honest person, okay, you know, but the only thing that's being withheld
is the part that's in dispute. Nobody is losing the principal. So
that should show that we don't make a קנס kenas to make
somebody lose the principal even if here the person, you know, the
liar is getting, you know, is not being hurt by this. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי השתא? hachi hasha? What type of comparison is that? התם ודאי
מנה למר ומנה למר הכא מי יימר דלאו כולי ערובי עריב? Hatam
vadai maneh le-mar u-maneh le-mar hacha mi yeimar de-lav kulei iruvei ariv?
There,
each person definitely deserves a hundred dollars, and
meaning, so and, whereas, so if you were to impose a fine
there'd be two things. First of all, I mean I think the
stronger point that תוספות Tosafot says and maybe this is what the
גמרא Gemara means, is first of all if you were to impose
a fine you would definitely be hurting an honest person, okay, whereas
in the other case if you impose the fine,
you know, it's possible that it could be the person who was
entirely dishonest and intentionally mixed the whole thing up, right? So that
could be exactly sort of what the גמרא Gemara is saying. But
the גמרא Gemara could also be saying that the... there was no
violation done even the dishonest person, right? When I went ahead and
I gave Gloria the hundred dollars and I'm the one that's really
lying, right, there's no violation done with the hundred dollars as it
were that she owes me. The hundred dollars is really my hundred
dollars, right? That was complete... so I'm lying about the extra hundred
but there's nothing about that first hundred whereas in the case by
the grain maybe it was completely clean grain and I intentionally mixed
in the entire
amount, so it's not like there's an amount that's a
violation, right? This is... no, if this is the first four percent
which is tolerable and this is the extra one percent, so which
part did I intentionally mix? Did I intentionally mix this? Okay, maybe
I intentionally mixed the whole thing. So therefore the whole thing deserves
to be fined. It's not like you're fining even... even the part
that he was innocent about. Maybe I wasn't innocent about this part.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says here we're more entitled to say fine
the whole thing because I would say two reasons. One the גמרא
Gemara is explicit about it, but A, certainly, it's like well okay
well A he wasn't well the גמרא Gemara let's start with the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says A, he could be that he
wasn't even innocent about this, it could be the entire amount was
what he mixed in. And B, you know in this case you're
not definitely hurting an innocent party. Whereas in the case of this
that we both gave you know Gloria 100, if we were to
withhold all the money an innocent party is definitely being hurt. Okay
so here there's not necessarily an innocent party and B, he's not
necessarily even innocent about this amount. So therefore it's acceptable to fine
him the whole amount. Yes, go ahead.
I mean also just how much of a punishment is it? Like
if the guy bought that much meat and okay you happen to
get lucky that 4% can be mixed in with it. So like
making you like pay back that amount isn't really...
Right. You mean because at the end of the day anyway it's
a fine that it was acceptable to have that amount, but at
the end of the day you're still just giving somebody what he
paid for.
Right, good point too, yes.
But in the בבא מציעא Bava Metzia case you also have רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi coming in with the...
Excellent. So that's the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says according to the approach that we don't make
a fine we can accept why you don't make a fine. A,
there's a definite innocent party and B, that you know there's the
base amount was not in violation as opposed to here it all
might have been in violation. So תא שמע מסיפא, Tashma misseifa, fine,
let's look at the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi position as Gloria reminds
us. אמר רבי יוסי אם כן מה הפסיד הרמאי. Amar Rabbi Yossi
im kein mah hifsid harama'i. So if that's all you do is
hold the third hundred,
this is what I said, it's not necessarily punishing, it's also preventative.
If there's no consequence what's going to stop people from lying? So
אלא הכל יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו. Elow hakol yehei munach ad
sheyavo Eliyahu. So actually it all gets withheld and that way you
know of course at the end of the day the honest person
innocent person might lose out as well right because he might need
the hundred dollars more than the liar person and he might be
willing to tolerate some type of a פשרה. peshara. But anyway but
nevertheless he says we have to have a consequence or we're not
going to stop the liars. So the גמרא Gemara says so it
seems that at least according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that's consistent
is at least רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi lined up with this idea
that you at least according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that you
have to hold the whole $300. You would think definitely according to
him it would mean that you would have to reimburse for the
entire amount. Would that logically follow? So the גמרא Gemara says no
you can even say רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi doesn't logically lead to
the same conclusion here.
The גמרא Gemara says like this. הכי השתא, Hachi hashta, what type
of comparison is that? התם ודאי איכא רמאי, Hasam vadai ika ramai,
הכא מי יימר דרובו עריב. hacha mi yeimar de-rubo ariv.
The opposite way of saying it, in that case even though there's
an innocent party that's losing out somebody is definitely lying. So when
somebody is definitely lying we need to have a consequence or we're
going to let people get away with murder. You know we might
as well just go ahead broadcast and say that it's open field
day for anybody who wants to lie because even when we know
there's a liar it's very clear you can get away with things.
Okay so in that case or a deceiver. So in that case
we have to make it because there's definitely somebody there who's cheating.
In this case maybe it happened that innocently 5% got mixed up
and not 4%. So it's not so clear here that we would
make such a fine when you don't know. So on the one
hand it's possible here the entire thing was in violation and that
no innocent party is being hurt. So that's an argument to why
here we're more prepared. On the other hand it's possible here that
the guy's totally innocent. So you could go either way with this
case and it doesn't line up with that debate.
Okay let's look at another debate. תא שמע. Tashma. So this is
fun because now we get to look at when do we when
do we say we're going to make a fine and when do
we extend it to even the
principal as opposed to just the amount that's in violation. תא שמע.
Tashma. שטר שיש בו ריבית. Shtar she-yesh bo ribit. So you have
a document that says I am borrowing $100 from Jenna with a
5% you know annual interest rate. Okay so there you go. That's
a שטר shtar in violation of a biblical prohibition of ריבית. ribit.
So can Jenna now collect the hundred dollars from me? She certainly
can't collect the five dollars at the end of the year that
I owe her for the ריבית. ribit. Okay but can she at
least collect the hundred dollars? Or are we going to say that
since she lent me money here with ריבית ribit she can't collect
anything? All
right so שטר שיש בו ריבית קונסו ואינו גובה לא את הקרן
ולא את הריבית דברי רבי מאיר. Shtar she-yesh bo ribit koniso ve-eino
goveh lo es ha-keren ve-lo es ha-ribit, divrei Rabbi Meir. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says you don't collect anything. So that's a great
example. Talk about a base amount and an added amount. Because the
added amount was in violation we're going to fine her even the
whole principal and she can't collect anything. So here too we should
say that if this amount was in violation then you now we're
going to force you to now you know pay back the whole
amount. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי השתא Hachi hashta what type
of comparison is that?
התם
משעת... Hasam misat... So from the very moment of the loan or
the writing of the document or even תוספות's Tosafos point that even
if no document had been written, the loaning of the money, clearly
there was a violation of the prohibition. So we know, there's no
question, Jena was in violation and if she was in violation and
the violation took place in the context of the loan, we're gonna,
you know, make her lose the entire loan. הכא מי יימר דעבד
הכי? hacha mi yeimar de'avad hachi? Here,
who says that the person ever did anything wrong? It could have
been just sometimes it happens, 5% and not 4%. You don't know
the person did anything wrong. So it's similar to the prank before,
like ודאי איכא רמאי. vadai ika ramai. Here it's like ודאי איכא
עבריין, vadai ika avaryan, right? Here there's definitely a violator, so to
be very heavy about it. In the other case, in the case
of the wheat and, you know, maybe it was all very innocent.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, תא שמע מסיפא, ta shema miseifa,
but look, that issue is debated between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים. Chachamim. The חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say
גובה את הקרן ואינו גובה את הריבית. goveh es hakeren ve'eino goveh
es haribis. No, Jena can still collect the principal. So here
there was a she was ודאי vadai in violation and we let
her collect the principal. So if that's true in that case, then
here certainly where you don't even know if the person is in
violation, you should say that okay, you know, give back the 1%
but you don't have to give back the 4%. Okay, how is
it different?
So the גמרא Gemara says הכי השתא? hachi hashta? No, what type
of comparison is that? התם ודאי קרנא דהתירא
הוא. hasham vadai karna deheteira hu.
No, because you say the opposite way. Yes, Jena was definitely in
violation for charging me ריבית, ribbis, but there was no prohibition of
lending me the $100. The prohibition was putting interest on top of
it, but the $100 itself, that loan, was not a now you've
pointed you don't look at it as a package. You don't say
there was a loan with ריבית ribbis the entire loan was in
violation. No, the loan was actually מותר, mutter, is actually a מצוה
mitzvah if it hadn't been ריבית. ribbis. Okay, and the ריבית ribbis
was a violation that took place together with the loan, but the
loan itself was legitimate.
הכא מי יימר דכולי
לאו
אבירזי?
hacha
mi yeimar dekulei lav avirzi? Here
maybe the entire amount was intentionally mixed in. Now after that I
think I'm already a little bit less sympathetic to that argument, you
know? I feel like if they're loaning money with interest that colors
the whole nature of the loan, right? It means that the whole
point of a loan is for, you know, the other person to
be making money off of it. You're using the loan to collect
interest. It's hard to sort of separate the loan was היתר, heter,
the interest was איסור. issur. We're gonna allow the היתר heter to
stand. Okay, but at least the גמרא Gemara says at least conceptually
you can do that as opposed to if the entire amount was
mixed together, then it's all in violation. Now before we go on
with the next proof, some interesting side points. First of all, תוספות
Tosafos has an interesting question. When רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you
can't collect the loan, does that just mean we tear up the
שטר? shtar? Let's say you bring other evidence, witnesses that saw the
money being lent. So is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir just saying the
שטר shtar has ריבית ribbis is like a פסול שטר pasul shtar
and you tear it up, but if he brings witnesses to testify
that the money was lent he could still collect the principal? Or
do we say no, the whole loan is not collectible? So תוספות
Tosafos says the פשט pshat of the language is that the whole
loan is not collectible and תוספות Tosafos says that actually makes sense
because it's not that the שטר shtar was in violation. The loan
was in violation. The lending with ריבית ribbis is a prohibition whether
you do it with a שטר, shtar, you don't do it with
a שטר. shtar. So since the loan was in violation, now he
says that might be different to compare the other case. There's a
הלכה halacha that שטרי חוב המוקדמין פסולין. shtarei chov hamukdamin pesulin. Okay,
I lend Gloria a thousand dollars and today is what's today, April
25th, and we write on it April 1st. Now that's invalid. Why
is that invalid? Because then if Gloria can't pay me, I'm going
to be able to use it as a lien from April 1st
to collect a plot of land that she sold to Jena, you
know, three days ago. Okay, so in that case the שטר shtar
we throw it out. Can I still collect the hundred dollars if
I have witnesses? So the answer is yes. The שטר shtar is
invalid because the שטר shtar was done in a wrong way. It
claimed to have a false lien and it claimed earlier whatever. But
the problem was the שטר. shtar. The problem wasn't the loan. In
that case, the שטר shtar gets thrown out and we can't use
it and we probably can't even use it even to collect my
legitimate lien. We treat the whole thing as though there was no
שטר shtar for this, no lien for it, because the שטר shtar
was in violation. But if I have other witnesses I can still
collect the loan. And תוספות Tosafos contrasts that to a ריבית ribbis
case. By ריבית ribbis the problem wasn't the שטר, shtar, the problem
was the loan and according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir at least
that says that you can't collect, you can't collect even even without
the שטר, shtar, even with עדים eidim you can't collect the loan
at all. So that's like one important, like, you know, and logical
conceptual distinction. Yes, Jena.
Is there also a prohibition of borrowing with interest?
Yes. So you're going to have probably the next question that תוספות
Tosafot asks which is what?
Which is, doesn't the person just get to keep the money and
then that's it?
So, oh well, so why do we only find the lender and
not the borrower? So תוספות Tosafot has two good reasons. I mean,
one sort of is like, you know, the lender obviously doesn't want
to be borrowing with ריבית. ribbit. And you know, so the lender
is—I mean not the lender, the borrower. The borrower always is doing
things because he has no choice. So first of all, it's not
going to like help so much, you know, and the lender is
the one that has a high incentive. So you want to be
fining and punishing the person who's got the motivation and the incentive
and the options, and not the person who doesn't really have the
options and is doing it because they're forced to. Number one. Number
two, תוספות Tosafot says, what are you going to fine the borrower?
The borrower doesn't have any money. They have what they owe! The
hundred dollars that they owe.
I know, so what are you going to do? You're going to
make him pay the other guy more? No oh—oh you mean according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that he's benefiting, it's like a חוטא
נשכר. choteh niskar. If that's the case then you're not fining him,
it's that he's actually benefiting. Right, that's an interesting point. Yeah, but
the תוספות's Tosafot's point is like look, like I mean I guess
you could make them all pay בית דין. Beit Din. Like you've
got to pay your חוב chov to בית דין Beit Din and
you don't—I guess you could do that. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot said
look, if you have to choose, obviously you, you know, you fine
the person with the money, not the person without the money, but
also you fine the person with the incentive, not the one without.
But yes, תוספות Tosafot raises the חוטא נשכר choteh niskar question. The
other question, the final one is, is that there's not only does
the borrower and the lender transgress, you know who else transgresses? The
witnesses who signed the שטר. shtar. So תוספות Tosafot says I don't
understand, why is this not a שטר פסול? shtar pasul? The witnesses,
the moment they signed the שטר shtar they're being עובד over on
an עבירה aveirah of
assisting whatever ריבית. ribbit. So that should make even according to the
חכמים, Chachamim, when the חכמים Chachamim say it's valid, they presumably they
say the שטר shtar is valid. I mean not for the ריבית
ribbit part, the principle. So he says, why aren't they עדים פסולים?
edim psulim? They were עובד over on this עבירה. aveirah. So תוספות
Tosafot says, well, because this is a very important הלכה halacha about
עדים פסולים. edim psulim. He says that even if something is a
clear עבירה aveirah that makes you an עד פסול, ed pasul, if
people don't—if it's not the common perception,
it does not פסול pasul an עד. ed. So for example the
גמרא Gemara applies it to the prohibition of לא תחמוד. lo tachmod.
לא תחמוד Lo tachmod according to the גמרא Gemara is that if
I force you to give me something that I covet, you know,
that I desire of yours, and you don't really want to sell
it, even if I pay it you for it, I transgress לא
תחמוד. lo tachmod. But the גמרא Gemara says if I did pay
you for it, even though I would have transgressed, I'm not a
פסול עד, pasul ed, because people don't think that's the transgression of
לא תחמוד. lo tachmod. They think לא תחמוד lo tachmod is forcing
you to give it without me paying you for it. So תוספות
Tosafot says the—and that's actually very important in terms of contemporary questions,
right, when you have, you know, a major segment of the, of
the, you know, Jews are like non-observant, you know, would
does sort of the ignorance or the—of that it's a prohibition or
the perception that it's not a prohibition mean that doing the thing
does not make you a פסול עד. pasul ed. So that's what
תוספות Tosafot says why the witnesses would not be פסול עד. pasul
ed. Okay, so let's—now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע,
ta shma, let's do one more case. דתני רבין בר רב נחמן,
di-tani Rabin bar Rav Nachman, לא את המותר בלבד הוא מחזיר אלא
מחזיר לו את כל הרביעין כולם. lo et hamutar bilvad hu machazir
ella machazir lo et kol harivi'in kulam.
So here there's a משנה Mishnah later on that says that if
I go ahead and I buy from you a בית סאה. beit
se'ah. Okay, here gonna have to write—I'm gonna have to write this
here, give myself a little cheat sheet. I've got a בית סאה,
beit se'ah, okay. A בית כור, beit kor, this is now area
measurement. A בית כור beit kor is thirty בית סאה. beit se'ah.
That's the amount like that you used to plant it for that
amount of seed. And a בית סאה beit se'ah is fifty by
fifty אמות, amot, just if you're curious. Okay, but it is six
בית קב. beit kav. All right. And a בית קב beit kav
is four בית רובע. beit rova. Okay? Now you could see here
again, right, there's a רובע rova is a רובע הקב. rova hakav.
There's six קב kav to a סאה. se'ah. Okay? Now what the
משנה Mishnah says is I go ahead and I am buying, you
know, from Gloria here a בית כור. beit kor. Okay? It says
what I am—and I say—now if I say that I'm buying a
בית כור, beit kor, we go and we measure it. All right.
Let's say it's—you say this plot of land, I'm telling you it's
a בית כור, beit kor, it's an acre. We go and we
measure it. It was off a little bit. So if he said
מידה בחבל, mida b'chevel, which is a way of saying like, you
know, to the inch, okay, like, you know, by the, you know,
by the measuring—by by the ruler, then even if it's off a
little bit she has to reimburse me or I have to pay
her extra or whatever. If she says more or less, פחות או
יתר. pachot o yeter. It's a בית כור beit kor more or
less. Okay? Then it's allowed to be off by a certain amount.
How much is it allowed to be off? It's allowed to be
off one רובע rova per—now I'm trying to remember—one רובע rova per
סאה. se'ah. Which means so if there's thirty... So if there's thirty
סאה se'ah here and it's allowed to be off one רובע rova
per סאה, se'ah, it's allowed to be off a total of thirty
רובע rova for a בית כור, beis kor, okay?
So, one רובע, rova, how many רובע rova is there? That's meaning
like again, it's the 4 percent, right? One רובע rova is for
there's four רובע rova in a קב kav and six קב kav
in a סאה, se'ah, so if it's allowed to be off one
רובע rova per סאה, se'ah, it's 1/24th, that's about 4 percent. So
if I say more or less, it could be up up to
4 percent, which is a total of thirty רובע rova for the
entire בית כור. beis kor. Now, let's say it was actually even
more than that. Like, or even less than that, okay? The difference
was greater than that. So how much now do I have to
reimburse? I forget if I'm the seller. I'm the seller and I
sold it to Gloria, and it actually is more than that amount,
it's under that amount by even more. Or the opposite, it's over
that amount by even more. So now we have to make it
good. Do we make it good by just that extra? Right, this
is the same question, or do we now have to make it
good, pay back for everything? Okay, so רב Rav says, לא את
המותר בלבד הוא מחזיר, lo es hamosar bilvad hu machzir, if it
wound up that the land was like too much, let's say I
gave her too much. Okay? So she, and it's more, so it's
he doesn't give back just the overage, אלא מחזיר לו את כל
הרבעין כולן. ela machzir lo es kol hariva'in kulan. All the, so
we were allowed thirty רבעין rova'in for a
בית כור, beis kor, and it actually was off by thirty-one רבעין.
rova'in. So it's not enough to give me back one רובע, rova,
you have to now give me back all thirty-one רובע. rova. So
that seems exactly parallel to our case, right? So that seems once
you're giving it back, you have to make it all good. Okay,
so אלמא היכא דבעי אהדורי כולא מהדר, almah heicha d'ba'ei ahadurei kula
mehadar, when you give it back, you give it all back. Okay?
So that sounds like that's what's going on. Then it's not clear,
now we might not be talking about קנס, knas, we might be
talking about דין, din, right? A certain amount of being off is
tolerable. More than that, I'm לא מוחל lo mochel and it's the
full amount. So let's say the same in our case, more than
that it's the full amount. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי השתא.
hachi hashta. What type of comparison is that? I love when it
says הכי השתא, hachi hashta, I'm like, what did it come into
your mind to make that comparison? It seems like a pretty good
comparison. It seems like almost the exact same case except translated to
land. But the גמרא Gemara is saying, you know, land is not
the same as grain. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם הן חסר
הן יתר אמר ליה. hasam hen chaser hen yeser amar leh. There,
when it was sold, what allowed it to be off by a
certain amount was when you said, you said more or
less. It's a בית סאה, beis se'ah, it's
a בית כור beis kor more or less.
מיהו רביע לא חשיב, mihu revia lo chashiv, you know, this amount,
a quarter to a קב kav is to a סאה se'ah is
not significant. So that's within the more or less. יתר מרביע חשיב,
yeser mi'revia chashiv, more than
a quarter is significant. דכיון דחזי ליה לאיצטרופי בט' קבין, de'keivan de'chazi
lei le'itztarufei b'tesha kavin, once you have more than thirty סאה se'ah
of,
thirty רבעין, rova'in, you're off by more than thirty רבעין, rova'in, so
that's getting close to a plot of land, the total amount adds
up to a plot of land almost nine קב. kav. You can
do the math, it's really more than seven and a half, but
for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara thinks once it's more, it's getting
close to nine קב, kav, and that's a significant plot of land,
it all
combined. הוי ליה ארעא חשיבותא בפני נפשה והדרא. havei lei ara chashivusa
bifnei nafshah ve'hadra. Then it's a significant plot of land when you're
off by, when you have all those overages combining, and then nobody
is מוחל mochel on that and הדר hadar goes back. So what's
the real difference? So the real difference at the end of the
day is, is that the גמרא Gemara says at the end of
the day like a little extra dirt in my wheat, it could
be that I'm always going to be מוחל mochel on the first
4 percent and I'm just not מוחל mochel on the amount over
4 percent, so you give me back the amount over 4 percent.
But here, even when I say more or less, if the total
of the more or less is a big plot of land, then
then you know, that's something significant and then that's you're not מוחל
mochel on. So it really doesn't say like there's not a conceptual
difference, it just sort of says like at the end of the
day, you know, you might be more okay being מוחל mochel a
certain amount of wheat even with overage, but at a certain amount
of land, when it combines to a large amount, you want the
whole land reimbursed. Okay, so it really was a pretty good comparison
and in the end the גמרא Gemara just said the difference is
whether there's significance to that amount of land as opposed to significance
to that amount of wheat and we will sort of continue working
out this question.